Guide to the Alexander Griswold Cummins Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alexander Griswold Cummins papers
1865-1947
MS 157
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
(8 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, biographical sketches, correspondence of his wife, Evelyn Atwater Cummins, clippings, photographs, and memorabilia of Alexander G. Cummins. Correspondence makes up the largest part of the papers and is largely concerned with church matters in which he took a strong low church position.The papers show advocacy of Ernest M. Stires and Herbert Shipman in church elections and his defense of Lee W. Heaton of Texas who was charged with heresy. Many of the letters refer to articles in The Chronicle, a newspaper founded and edited by Cummins from 1901 until his death. Notable in the correspondence are Nicholas Murray Butler, H. L. Mencken, Lowell Thomas, and Franklin D. Roosevelt.
Cummins, Alexander Griswold, 1869-1946
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Evelyn Atwater Cummins, 1937-1947.
Scope and Contents
These papers consist of correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, and other items relating to Alexander Griswold Cummins, a Protestant Episcopal minister of the low church, evangelical party. Cummins was the founder in 1901 of The Chronicle and its editor until his death. He employed this journal in often bitter attacks against the Anglo-Catholic, high church party and against any hint of reunion with the church of Rome, and in warm support of the Protestant and constitutional aspects of the Protestant Episcopal Church and in support of modernist, liberal theology. Articles for The Chronicle provide much of the subject matter of the correspondence, both in terms of Cummins' research and polling of churchmen for their views on various controversial issues and in terms of reader reaction to his articles. Like The Chronicle, his correspondence provides a highly partisan view of Protestant Episcopal Church politics from the early 1900s through the 1940s. The struggle between high and low churchmen is a recurrent theme, as are efforts of the church hierarchy to assume greater authority, proper use of church funds, and any and all practices smacking of Anglo-Catholicism.
Cummins was involved in behind-the-scenes campaigning in behalf of Ernest M. Stires as low church candidate for bishop of New York in 1919-1920 (folders 92-102), and for the election of Herbert Shipman, another low churchman, as Suffragan Bishop of New York in 1921 (folders 117-131). Cummins was also active in combatting charges of heresy brought against the modernist Lee W. Heaton by the conservative Diocese of Texas in 1923-1925 and the resultant attempt by the conservatives to redefine the Creed (folders 62-75). In another dispute between a low church minister and his high church parish, Cummins generously helped find emergency financial aid and a new, more congenial parish (folders 57-61).
Not all of Cummins' papers are devoted to controversy. Correspondence, schedules, and memorabilia from preaching engagements in Great Britain are included (folders 21-24), as are correspondence and memorabilia relating to his 38th and 40th anniversaries at Christ Church (folders 27-39), and to other social events (folders 82-86, 129). Cummins' correspondence contains letters not only from most of the Protestant Episcopal bishops of his day, but also from prominent clergymen of other denominations in America and Britain, as well as a few letters from such notables as Nicholas Murray Butler, H. L. Mencken, Lowell Thomas, and Franklin D. Roosevelt. The correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent and subject. Cummins' original folder headings have been retained wherever possible.
Several short writings and a biographical sketch of Cummins are also included among the papers, as is some correspondence of his wife, Evelyn (Atwater) Cummins. The latter consists of letters of condolence for Cummins' death, letters on the merger of The Chronicle (of which she became the editor after his death) with The Southern Churchman in 1947, several notes from Sara Delano Roosevelt, and miscellaneous letters dealing for the most part with articles she had written. Other correspondence of Evelyn Cummins may be found interfiled with the correspondence of Alexander G. Cummins in folders 8, 28-39, and 87.
Other items in the Alexander Griswold Cummins Papers are an article about Cummins by Wilbur L. Caswell, newspaper clippings about Cummins and about the Protestant Episcopal Church, programs, invitations, and other printed matter, and photographs from anniversary dinners.
These papers were donated to Yale University by Evelyn Atwater Cummins in a series of gifts between 1937 and 1947.
For related materials in Manuscripts and Archives, see the Protestant Episcopal Bishops Collection (Ms. Gr. 21) and the E. Clowes Chorley Papers (Ms. Gr. 132). A small collection of autographs of Protestant Episcopal bishops assembled in part by E. Clowes Chorley and donated as part of the Alexander Griswold Cummins Papers by Evelyn Cummins has been transferred to the E. Clowes Chorley Papers. A list of the letters transferred can be found in the register file.
United States -- Politics and government; Clergy; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947; Cummins, Alexander Griswold, 1869-1946; Cummins, Evelyn Atwater, 1891-; Heaton, Lee Wilbert; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Shipman, Herbert, bp., 1869-1930; Stires, Ernest Milmore, 1866-1951; Thomas, Lowell, 1892-1981; Episcopal Church
- Inventory, 1865-(1913-1947); 3' (8 boxes)
  - Correspondence
    - Abbott, H. P. Almon, 1931-1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The American Missal, 1931 May-July (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - Anti-Moth Ball Society, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bell, Bernard Iddings, 1914-1926, undated (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
    - Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1936, 1938, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Christ Church (Reading, Pa.), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Church Unity Octave Council, 1928, 1935-1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 10-16)
    - The Churchman, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Committee of Twenty-Five, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Cook, Philip, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
    - Cummins, Alexander Griswold
      - Preaching engagements in England, 1934-1937 (Box 1, Folder 21-24)
      - Sermon in Westminster Abbey, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
      - 38th anniversary at Christ Church, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - 40th anniversary at Christ Church, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 28-39)
      - "Protestant Episcopal or Anglo catholic", 1945 February-May (Box 2, Folder 40-41)
    - Darlington, James H., 1921, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Episcopal Theological School, 1923-1924 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Fish, Stuyvesant, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Fiske, Charles, 1932-1934, undated (Box 3, Folder 45-48)
    - Fond du Lac, Diocese of, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Freeman, James E, 1933-1935 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Gilbert, Charles Kendall, 1916-1930 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Grammer, Carl E, 1913-1914 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Greer, David H, 1911-1915 (Box 3, Folder 53-54)
    - Haiti, Missionary District of, 1936 May-June (Box 3, Folder 55-56)
    - Hardin, Louis T., 1921-1922 (Box 3, Folder 57-61)
    - Heaton, Lee Wilbert, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 62-67)
    - Heaton, Lee Wilbert, 1924-1925, undated (Box 4, Folder 68-75)
    - Kenyon College, 1926, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 76-77)
    - Kent, E. A. Knox, bp. of, 1928-1936 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Lloyd, Arthur S., 1915-1931 (Box 4, Folder 79-80)
    - McKim, Randolph H., 1913-1914, undated (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Matthews, William R., 1936 September-October (Box 4, Folder 82-86)
    - Mencken, Henry Louis, 1933, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Murray, John G., 1926 September-October (Box 4, Folder 88-91)
    - New York, Diocese of
      - Election of bishop, 1919 May-July (Box 4, Folder 92-93)
      - Election of bishop, 1919 August-1921, undated (Box 5, Folder 94-102)
      - Convention, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 103)
      - Standing Committee, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - Parsons, Edward L, 1921-1933 (Box 5, Folder 105)
    - Pennsylvania, Diocese of: Journal of the 139th Convention, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 106)
    - Protestant Episcopal Society for Promoting Religion and Learning in the State of New York, 1914-1915 (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - Reiland, Karl, 1928-1934 (Box 5, Folder 108)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano, 1939-1941 (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - "Sad St. Alban's", 1937 (Box 5, Folder 110-113)
    - St. Luke's Hospital (Shanghai), 1936 November-December (Box 6, Folder 114-115)
      General
      See also: box 7, folders 141-143
    - Seaman, E. Cecil, 1926-1928, 1939 February (Box 6, Folder 116)
    - Shipman, Herbert, 1921, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 117-131)
    - Stires, Ernest Milmore, 1913, 1921-1935 (Box 7, Folder 132-135)
    - Thomas, Lowell, 1940-1941 (Box 7, Folder 136)
    - Török, John W., 1934-1936, undated (Box 7, Folder 137-140)
    - Trinity Church (New York, N.Y.), 1936-1938 (Box 7, Folder 141-143)
      See also: box 6, folders 114-115
    - World Alliance for Promoting International Friendship Through the Churches, 1916-1917 (Box 7, Folder 144)
    - General correspondence
      - B-W, 1913-1940, undated (Box 7, Folder 145-148)
      - Unidentified, 1913, 1941 (Box 7, Folder 149)
  - Writings
    - "The Never-ending Quest," The Christian World Pulpit, pp. 90-92, 1933 August 24 (Box 7, Folder 150)
    - "The Clove Valley Rod and Gun Club," Parts I and II, Game Breeder and Sportsman, 1934 Jan, February (Box 7, Folder 150)
    - Biographical sketch, undated (Box 7, Folder 151)
  - Cummins, Evelyn (Atwater): correspondence
    - Letters of condolence, 1946-1947 (Box 7, Folder 152)
    - The Chronicle, 1947 July (Box 7, Folder 153)
    - Roosevelt, Sarah D., 1939-1940 (Box 7, Folder 154)
    - General correspondence, B-V, 1924-1941, undated (Box 7, Folder 155)
      See also: box 1, folder 8
      See also: box 2, folders 28-39
      See also: box 4, folder 87
    - Cummins, Alexander Griswold, Sr.: ALS to Mrs. Bridgman, 1900 April 23 (Box 7, Folder 156)
    - Caswell, Wilbur Larremore: "Alexander V. G. Cummins, an American Gad-Fly," The Churchman, pp. 10-12, 1930 May 3 (Box 7, Folder 157)
    - Programs, invitations, and other printed matter, 1865, 1914, 1933-1947, undated (Box 7, Folder 158)
    - Newspaper clippings, [ca. 1930s-1940s] (Box 7, Folder 159)
    - Photographs, 1908, 1924, 1925 (Box 8, Folder 160)